{
  "age": 64,
  "background": "Professor of Government and Politics",
  "directory": "content/state-house/district-25",
  "district": 25,
  "dob": "12/24/1953",
  "education": "Ph.D Government & Politics MA Public Administration and Political Science",
  "filename": "stanley-onye.md",
  "full-name": "Stanley Onye",
  "jurisdiction": "Prince George's County",
  "last-name": "Onye",
  "party": "Democrat",
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "Do you support the findings of the Commission on Innovation and Excellence in Education? Are you committed to funding associated reforms, and if so, how?",
      "answer": "Yes I support the Finding. I am committed to funding the associated reforms. The reforms will offer a sea change in how we view education in Maryland, and it will usher in real progress, real hope. It will be funded through the casino revenue and contributions to the state/counties. The fund will be dedicated to funding education only and not deposited in the general fund, We also propose raising tax to fund education.",
      "shortname": "Kirwan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is Maryland’s transportation spending appropriately balanced between roads and transit? Does the state have the resources to meet its transportation needs? With the cancellation of the Red Line and the advent of BaltimoreLink, is the Baltimore region adequately served by transit?",
      "answer": "No.. The state has the resources to meet its transportation needs. The transit system (Metro) is funded through a combination of jurisdictional subsidies and federal grants, but does not have a dedicated funding . I do not believe that Baltimore region is adequately served by transit. This is because the region is congested and most roads need substantial improvement",
      "shortname": "Transportation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you support the legalization of recreational marijuana?",
      "answer": "Maryland has decriminalized small possession of marijuana. The passing of Senate Bill 364 in 2014 made the possession of less than 10 grams of recreational marijuana for personal use a civil offense that carries no jail time and a maximum fine of $100. However, possession of greater quantities is still a criminal offense. Carrying up to 50 pounds of marijuana is a misdemeanor, punishable by up to a year in jail and a $1,000 fine. Possession of quantities greater than 50 pounds is a felony in the state. Maryland also imposes minimum mandatory sentences for some marijuana-related offenses. However, I support the legalization of recreational marijuana as a first amendment right.",
      "shortname": "Marijuana"
    },
    {
      "question": "At a time when the federal government’s commitment to Chesapeake Bay restoration is questionable, what new steps should Maryland take to protect this resource?",
      "answer": "Maryland should impose penalties for those companies that pollute the bay. They should be charged to pay for the cleanup. The state should also control the amount of runoffs farmers are allowed to produce. There should be a massive education of use of pesticides, and other harmful materials. Government should form federal/state and private partnership to come up withy recommendations and possible resources to protect the resources.",
      "shortname": "Chesapeake Bay"
    },
    {
      "question": "What steps should Maryland take to ensure the broadest possible access to affordable health care?",
      "answer": "Maryland should adopt a single payer model to ensure the broadest possible access to affordable healthcare. Single-payer national health insurance, also known as \"Medicare for all,\" is a system in which a single public or quasi-public agency organizes health care financing, but the delivery of care remains largely in private hands. Under a single-payer system, all residents of the U.S. would be covered for all medically necessary services, including doctor, hospital, preventive, long-term care, mental health, reproductive health care, dental, vision, prescription drug and medical supply costs.  The program would be funded by the savings obtained from replacing today's inefficient, profit-oriented, multiple insurance payers with a single streamlined, nonprofit, public payer, and by modest new taxes based on ability to pay. Premiums would disappear; 95 percent of all households would save money. Patients would no longer face financial barriers to care such as co-pays and deductibles, and would regain free choice of doctor and hospital. Doctors would regain autonomy over patient care.",
      "shortname": "Health Care"
    },
    {
      "question": "What role should the state play in helping Baltimore address violent crime?",
      "answer": "The state should play a very active role in helping Baltimore address violent crime. The state should direct more than 500 state parole and probation officers to partner with the Baltimore Police Department to track down and arrest repeat criminals who have parole and probation violations. The U.S. Marshal Service should begin sweeping the city with  task force officers. They will work with the state and city on serving warrants and carrying patrols in many troubled areas. More funds should be made available to help pay for overtime and other associated services.",
      "shortname": "Crime"
    },
    {
      "question": "How would you characterize Maryland’s business climate? What can the state do to foster the creation of more family-supporting jobs?",
      "answer": "Maryland business climate is improving but state intervention to attract more businesses. The state should set aside dedicated funds so that small business owners can have easy access to start off funds. Business regulation should be streamlined and business taxes reduced. Set aside funds to encourage businesses to relocate to Maryland.",
      "shortname": "Business Climate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you support the creation of a non-partisan, independent body to draw legislative and congressional district maps after each census?",
      "answer": "I fully support the creation of a non-partisan body to draw legislative and congressional district maps after each census. This will ensure fairness and remove political influence in determining districts.",
      "shortname": "Redistricting"
    },
    {
      "question": "Does the Law Enforcement Officers Bill of Rights adequately balance protections for police and the public? Should it be changed, and if so, how?",
      "answer": "The Law Enforcement Officers Bill of Rights does not adequately balance protections for police and the public. It should be modified or changed. As currently structured, LEOBR grants police officers special rights when they are investigated for misconduct, imposes significant impediments to conducting an adequate investigation and takes responsibility for discipline away from police chiefs. Significantly, LEOBR is a substantial barrier to transparency that precludes meaningful civilian oversight of the disciplinary process. And because of these flaws, a great many people have no faith that the officers who police our communities will be held accountable when they act improperly.  Several changes are needed to bring the statute in line with what is granted to public employees generally and what is granted in other states to their police. Currently superiors may not question their officers for 10 days following an incident. Not only are officers entitled to an attorney, union attorneys are usually available to them immediately. There is no need for an additional waiting period. Ten days simply impedes investigation and significantly delays the ability of police departments to communicate effectively with the public about what happened. The new law should revise the waiting period.",
      "shortname": "LEOBR"
    },
    {
      "question": "What strategy would you adopt to address the opioid addiction and overdose crisis?",
      "answer": "Establish more drug treatment centers and hire adequate drug counselors promptly evaluate and recommend treatment. Have doctors reduce the amount painkillers and other drugs they prescribe. Government should declare a drug and overdose crisis emergency so as to direct resources to treatment and counseling.",
      "shortname": "Opioids"
    },
    {
      "question": "What if anything should the state do to address income inequality?",
      "answer": "We have to find ways of redistributing wealth. Government should create jobs that will pay meaningful living wage. There should be a government and private partnership to review wage structure and training program. People should be trained in those hard to fill jobs that pay well so that people can find jobs and get off welfare and unemployment.",
      "shortname": "Income inequality"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do the state’s Public Information Act and open meetings laws adequately ensure Marylanders’ ability to exercise oversight of the government?",
      "answer": "No. We should strengthen the whistle blowing laws that adequately protect people that are willing to provide information of waste and mismanagement. The laws should be loosened so that citizens that monitor the functions of government.",
      "shortname": "Transparency"
    }
  ],
  "race": "state-house",
  "residence": "Upper Marlboro",
  "social-tw": "StanleyOnye2018",
  "survey-response": true,
  "title": "Stanley Onye"
}
